Jacob
He Faced Danger to Protect His Family NEAR the end of his life, Jacob chose two words to describe his years, “few” and “distressing.” (Gen. 47:9) He did have his share of hardships! Earlier in his life, he had to run away to distant Haran because his own brother wanted to kill him. In Haran, Jacob fell in love with Rachel, but her father, Laban, tricked him into marrying Rachel’s older sister first. So Jacob had two wives​—who did not get along. For decades, Laban employed Jacob but repeatedly tried to swindle him. Yet, Jacob showed remarkable courage, faith, and endurance. One day, Jehovah told Jacob that it was time to leave Haran and return home to Canaan. But that could be dangerous, for Laban was possessive and greedy. Jacob consulted with his family and then gathered them and fled without telling Laban. When Laban learned of it, he gathered his men and pursued. He finally caught up with the family and harshly criticized Jacob for leaving. Laban even said, menacingly: “It is in my power to do harm to you.” But Jacob courageously corrected Laban. He pointed out that Laban had treated him unfairly and deviously for years. At the same time, Jacob had been willing to pursue peace. The two men parted on friendly terms. What enabled Jacob to make peace with aggressive family members and even to wrestle with a mighty angel? Jacob had yet to face his twin brother, Esau. Decades earlier, their mother, Rebekah, had warned Jacob that Esau wanted to kill him. Esau was convinced that Jacob had cheated him out of his father’s blessing. Now, Jacob sought to make peace. He learned that Esau was heading toward him and his family, leading 400 men. Jacob sent servants ahead to meet Esau, taking valuable gifts to him. But would that be enough to quell Esau’s anger? We read: “Jacob became very frightened and anxious.” Then something amazing happened. In the predawn hours, Jacob caught sight of a stranger. It was an angel of Jehovah, and the angel began to struggle with Jacob. Sensing that the angel had some blessing to offer, Jacob courageously grappled with him for hours. Jacob refused to give up​—though he was then 97 years old and hopelessly outmatched. He fought hard. He even wept. (Hos. 12:4) Jacob was determined, convinced that any blessing from Jehovah was worth the struggle. At dawn, with a mere touch, the angel put Jacob’s hip socket out of joint. Yet, the angel also told Jacob something wonderful​—that his name was now Israel. The name had meaning; it referred to contending with God. Jacob certainly had persisted and had exerted himself in order to gain a blessing from Jehovah. Jacob limped back to his family. In the distance, there was Esau, approaching with his 400 men. Jacob went ahead, alone, to face them all. As he approached Esau, Jacob bowed low seven times. Then Esau ran toward him. But Esau drew no weapon. Instead, he opened his arms wide and embraced Jacob! The two men wept. Jacob’s generous gifts and his humble manner had completely disarmed Esau. Perhaps he admired Jacob’s courage as well. Jacob had found a way to make peace with his brother. For the rest of his life, Jacob limped because of his injured hip. And he faced many more hardships. But he surely never regretted his decisions to obey Jehovah or to struggle with that angel. In time, a wonderful promise Jehovah had made to him was fulfilled​—Israel became a great nation. (Gen. 28:14) Moreover, Jehovah was often called “the God of Jacob.” (Ex. 3:6) Jesus Christ himself used that phrase. He added that Jehovah “is a God, not of the dead, but of the living, for they are all living to him.” (Luke 20:37, 38) So Jacob’s future is assured. In the new world, his years will be long beyond counting and happy beyond measure! Read the Bible account: Genesis 27:41-45; 31:1-29, 36-55; 32:1–33:16 
